<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://amy-hood.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://amy-hood.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-07-31T02:06:17+00:00</updated><id>https://amy-hood.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Data analyst, facilitator and strategist. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">when the metrics have no mission</title><link href="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2025/when-the-metrics-have-no-mission/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="when the metrics have no mission"/><published>2025-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2025/when-the-metrics-have-no-mission</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2025/when-the-metrics-have-no-mission/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/neom_mountains.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A mountain view, with a lone figure looking at the view. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@neom?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">NEOM</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-person-standing-on-top-of-a-cliff-207NEuFvjlg?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <h2 id="introduction-on-trends">introduction: on trend(s)</h2> <p>For most organizations, metrics are no longer new. It’s not cutting-edge to talk about measuring and monitoring success, even if most organizations still struggle to do it well. (Once, when pressed, a senior fundraising executive told me that bringing in $500,000 in donations was success for a large campaign because the number “just felt right.” Absolutely no shade to her – I’d wager that more metrics are done on intuition than we admit.) The tricky thing is, as metrics lose their sparkle, a lot of organizations are left with an unsettling sense that they should already be doing it. Doing the metric thing. And that, in fact, is actually quite hard to do.</p> <p>It’s hard to imagine where your team should be in a year, when you have an immediate, crushing to-do list today. It’s hard to track the metrics that matter, when the data you have is irrelevant, unreliable, or otherwise unusable. It’s hard to build a culture that uses metrics effectively, when so many people have learned that metrics equate to punishment and blame. All of which is to say it’s unsurprising to see organizations spending a lot of time tracking metrics they can’t quite articulate the importance of, don’t use in decision-making, and/or overblow to make unsubstantiated claims of success. (“We trained 100 people, we’re changing the world!”)</p> <p>The underlying thesis of this blog post is simple:</p> <blockquote> <p>Any metric that is worth tracking, reporting on, publishing somewhere internally or externally, is worth articulating a goal for. An imperfect goal that’s used is better than none at all. Without it, the metrics don’t (really) matter.</p> </blockquote> <p>The first half of this post will lay out the reasons why your metrics deserve the time a goal takes to write. You may already be thinking: “Of course, metrics need goals – but it’s not that simple!” You may not feel you have the time to write goals, or you may be in a transition period, or your metrics are mandated by some outside force. Sometimes the menagerie of things organizations track without clear motivation is a result of real limitations. I hear you. In the latter half of this blog post, I’ll propose a process on how you might write a goal that can be written rapidly, while still providing value to you and your team.</p> <p>I am writing with the assumption that you do not need to be convinced that metrics are a worthwhile management tool, or that data makes decision-making better. If that’s you and you’ve found your way to my blog, I invite you to read my <a href="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-longer-introduction/">post</a> about my own journey into data work before diving into this one.</p> <h3 id="quick-definition-break">quick definition break</h3> <p>Because a lot of organizations use the same terms to signify vastly different things, I hope you’ll forgive a brief pause for definitions. These definitions avoid describing an ideal state – that’s what the rest of the blog post is for!</p> <p><strong>Mission</strong>: A paragraph that describes the end state a team is working towards, including what the team does, who it does it for, why, and the impact they’re trying to achieve.</p> <p><strong>Goal</strong>: A written statement that describes the desired outcome of work. Goals can represent the work at any level of the organization over any time period. They may connect directly to a stated mission, or to other, larger goals at higher levels of the organization.</p> <p><strong>Objective</strong>: A written statement that describes a milestone or subset of a goal. Objectives are statements that the team hypothesizes must be true in order for a goal to be reached.</p> <p><strong>Metric</strong>: Any quantifiable number that a team uses to understand or describe its work. Metrics can connect to objective or goal statements.</p> <ul> <li>Performance metrics define real or perceived success for a team. Performance metrics should be all or mostly in the team’s direct control.</li> <li>Contextual metrics define the operational environment the team is working in, that may affect its ability to perform.</li> </ul> <p>Okay, back to business!</p> <h2 id="part-1-your-metrics-should-have-a-goal">part 1: your metrics should have a goal</h2> <p>For those who prefer an outline (guilty), here’s what you can expect in this section:</p> <ol> <li><a href="#on-ghost-goals">On Ghost Goals</a>: Your goals may not be written, but they can still haunt you.</li> <li><a href="#beans-beans-the-magical-fruit">Beans, Beans, the Magical Fruit</a>: Even a million beans is still a pile of beans.</li> <li><a href="#its-just-not-that-deep">It’s Just Not That Deep</a>: Lower your bar for good-enough goals.</li> </ol> <h3 id="on-ghost-goals">on ghost goals</h3> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/shaylyn_ghosts.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Four people dressed as ghosts, each wearing sunglasses. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@mpadb?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Shaylyn</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-group-of-birds-standing-on-a-rock-in-a-grassy-area-2oMdfUR-RkQ?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <p>Every time I’ve been in a conversation about a metric without an explicit goal, I’ve been surprised by the presence of an implicit one. This “ghost goal” is in the room, shaping how people talk about the metric and how to interpret its results. It might show up in someone arguing that a spike doesn’t matter, or encouraging a change to how the metric is calculated. If you start documenting the reasons why people are making these suggestions, you probably have the beginnings of a goal.</p> <p>Here’s a hypothetical that might better illustrate the point: Samantha runs a small nonprofit that provides coding classes for kids. The organization hosts classes in community centers, after-school programs, and libraries across the city, taught by professors from the local college. The organization tracks the total number of attendees per class, as volume seems like the natural metric. As Samantha reviews performance of different classes by location, she notes to her team that there’s one location that has consistently lower attendance than all the others. When she suggests cutting this class in favor of offering an additional time at their highest-attended location, her team disagrees. Someone notes that while few, the kids that do come to the class attend consistently. Another raises that there are no other coding classes available in the area, given that the neighborhood’s school doesn’t offer the topic. Someone else suggests that the other locations wouldn’t seem so well-attended if we filtered out attendees who only attended once, or didn’t stay for the whole class.</p> <p>It’s hard to resolve the disagreement on Samantha’s team without articulating more about the perceived value of the class itself. Are we trying to expose kids to coding concepts, or are we hoping they walk away with more advanced skills? Which kids are we hoping take advantage of this service? It may feel to Samantha that the team doesn’t trust the metric, or isn’t on-board with data-driven decision-making. In my humble opinion, that’s not the root of the disagreement – it’s the goal. If the team gets on the same page about what the value the classes should deliver, the decision on whether to cut the low-attended class will be easy.</p> <p>That’s the thing about ghost goals: they haunt. It feels like you’re arguing about the right math to use, or how to interpret a metric, but the core disagreement are two valid, conflicting interpretations of a goal that has yet to be made corporeal. Taking the time to write down a goal, even if it’s a poorly-written one, grounds a team in a shared reality.</p> <p>I’m simplifying a lot of real-world complexities here, but I hope the point comes through: Why spend time disagreeing about ghost goals when you could be having more productive conversations about real ones?</p> <h3 id="beans-beans-the-magical-fruit">beans, beans, the magical fruit</h3> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/shelley-pauls_beans.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A picture of many, multi-colored beans. (Still just beans.) Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@shelleypauls?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Shelley Pauls</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/assorted-colored-bean-lot-t4X660oKiYs?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <p>One of my favorite phrases in the evaluation community is “bean-counting” – a term for when organizations count what they can count, for no other reason than they can count it. Imagine a person at a table, counting a pile of beans: they place an index finger on each individual bean, name its number in the pile (“Seven!”) , and move it to the side. One, two, a thousand. Why spend the time to count beans? After all, even a million beans is still just a pile of beans.</p> <p>Your metrics may not be bean-counters, but without a goal, how do you know?</p> <p>I’m not going to wax poetic about the value of goals. I work in performance management, and I’m biased. I recently found an old Girl Scouts vest of mine with an achievement patch with “Ask me about my goals!” embroidered on it. I could genuinely wear that patch today and it’d be no less true than it was when I was eight years old. Even so, I know why goals can be hard to write and maintain, and the reasons why organizations struggle to write good ones. (I do work in performance management.) There are real pressures that make “just doing the work” seem an attractive alternative to the convening, consensus-building, and iterating processes that often accompany goal-writing.</p> <p>The thing that goals do really well, though, is answer why. Without a goal, you’re likely to come up empty when answering for why what you’re counting matters – or worse, come up with multiple, different answers depending on who you ask. There are, of course, the metrics organizations track because someone else told them they had to (e.g., the Board, the funder, the donors, the communications team), but even in those cases, it’s still a worthwhile line of questioning. Why does the Board, the donors, the communications team want that number? What do they think it tells them, and do we agree?</p> <p>Without a documented justification for tracking the metric (e.g., a goal), your metrics may very well be bean-counters. Counting to count. No one wants to spend precious time and resources counting a pile of beans, and the only way to ensure you’re not doing that is to write a goal.</p> <h3 id="its-just-not-that-deep">it’s just not that deep</h3> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/marisol-falcon_pool.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="200" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Steps into the shallow end of a swimming pool. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@solfarre?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Marisol Falcón</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-blue-swimming-pool-with-a-white-wall-D9kqA2323Ws?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <p>I’m going to make the case that your goals don’t have to be good.</p> <p>There is truly so much literature out there about how to write a good goal. Different philosophies about how and when to write them, what style to use, what level is ideal, how they should connect to other parts of the organization, how to ensure they’re ambitious and measurable and right. In my current role, I’ve written our recommendations for how to write a good goal. It’s easy to get overwhelmed with all the seemingly contradictory information out there. It’s even easier to put off writing a goal at all, because you want the time to do it right, at the right time.</p> <p>My husband works in start-ups. If you ask him about goals, he’ll lament that he’s never seen a goal stay relevant for more than six months. The fast-paced, existential environment of a start-up requires an agility that can make goal-writing feel like a waste of time. And while I would not recommend the same style of goals for organizations across industries or maturity, I think the observation is relevant for most of us. Goals change. They should change. So why do we get stuck on writing perfect ones?</p> <p>The incremental benefits of documenting goals for your metrics now – ridding yourself of the confusion that accompanies ghost goals, affirming that your metrics aren’t bean-counters, creating a shared language for your work – far outweigh the detriments of an imperfect goal. That imperfect goal will still help your work improve, as long as it’s used alongside a monitored metric. You’ll know your work better, and know how to write a better goal next time.</p> <p>The key to this is that your goals have to be used to be useful. There is no point to writing goals, perfect or not, if they’re only looked at when you’re proposing a budget or making a communications push. Write the imperfect goal, but refer to it often. Bring it up in your team meetings, use it when you talk to others about your work, and include it in your reporting. If you have goals that no one on your team could rattle off when asked, you’re doing it wrong.</p> <h2 id="part-2-getting-started-the-practical-way">part 2: getting started, the practical way</h2> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/kelly-sikkema_papers.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A notepad with a pen on top of it. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@kellysikkema?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Kelly Sikkema</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-pen-sitting-on-top-of-a-notebook-on-top-of-a-wooden-table-e0djo08-Ev8?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <p>I don’t know how your organization does (or doesn’t) do goals, so I don’t know how wild the suggestion I’m about to make is, but I’ll make it anyway: No matter where you sit in your organization, write the goal.</p> <p>If you’re an individual contributor, that might look like taking the 3-5 metrics your team most often uses to describe its work, and writing hypotheses to test with different stakeholders. You could frame competing hypotheses of your ghost goal as a “this or that” question: “Are we trying to accomplish X or Y when we do Z?” No team can achieve everything, and to the extent you can, I hope you can help your team resist the urge to say both. As an individual contributor, you can’t commit your team to goals, but you may get clarity that helps your work right now.</p> <p>If you manage a team, you likely have more say on your team’s goals, so it’ll be up to you to evaluate your circumstances. The ideal situation is a deeper reflection on your team’s mission and strategy, but I know there’s many times where that’s not feasible to do immediately. If, for whatever reason, you cannot do more robust reflection, I recommend identifying the 3-5 metrics your team uses most to describe its work, and writing something out. Share the draft with your team and your leadership, and keep it light – “This is how I’m thinking about the work we’re doing right now. Do you see it the same way? We can definitely change things as we go.” The hope is to create some initial clarity, not solve it all.</p> <h3 id="goals-vs-objectives">goals vs. objectives</h3> <p>Before I dive into recommendations for writing goals, I want to share a bit about how objectives should connect to goals. (I shared a bit about how I’m defining goals and objectives earlier <a href="#quick-definition-break">here</a>.)</p> <p>Goals describe why. Objectives describe what and how. I typically write objectives as statements that, when all added together, make the goal a reality. These may be milestones or projects that address the same problem from different angles. Either way, objectives operationalize a larger goal, and typically describe the work that you’re doing right now. It may feel the most “real” to you, because the work you touch on a day-to-day basis.</p> <p>If you don’t have written goals right now, I’d guess that your metrics are at the objective level. In my recommendations below, I have you start by writing an objective that describes your current metric, and then scaffold a goal – your “why” – atop it.</p> <h3 id="writing-a-rapid-goal">writing a rapid goal</h3> <p>I want to provide a very practical, very fast way to write a goal, using metrics that already exist. This will not produce a perfect goal – that’s not the point! – but it should help you right now, until you have the space and time for a more intentional process.</p> <ol> <li><strong>Write what you’re tracking right now:</strong> Use a formula: verb + thing you’re tracking + a target value. The target is likely wrong at this stage, but I’ve found it helpful to put a placeholder at the beginning as a part of brainstorming. It makes the work feel real – and you don’t have to share it with anyone until you’re sure it’s right. Write an uninspiring, messy first draft, and resist revising. This is a draft objective.</li> <li><strong>Pull it up a level:</strong> Why is your team doing this work? What is it achieving? Imagine the world where you meet or exceed the target you put in as a placeholder: in that world, what would you have that you didn’t have before? It’s hard to reverse-engineer a goal from a metric, so don’t overthink it. Write a hypothesis, and don’t try to make it perfect. This is a draft goal for the objective you wrote in step one.</li> <li><strong>Refine:</strong> Now it’s time to do some quick sanity checks on the content, not the phrasing. You want to double check that you wrote down what you’re actually trying to do. Here are some questions I find useful for ensuring my content is on the mark: <ul> <li><strong>Specifics:</strong> Go through each part of your goal and objective statement, and make sure you’re as specific as you can be. Imagine all the ways your objective could be misinterpreted. If there are some interpretations that don’t align to what you’re trying to achieve, close the gaps in your language to exclude them.</li> <li><strong>Cause-and-Effect:</strong> Do you really think your objective is a requirement for your goal to happen? If not, either your goal or your objective is not quite right yet. If your goal is right but the objective is wrong, it’s possible that your metric is a bean-counter and you need to track something else (or something additional).</li> <li><strong>End-state:</strong> With a general timeline in mind for your goal (e.g., however long you think it will take to complete the objective you wrote), ask yourself: is this really where I want to land? Would my team be satisfied with the reality as-written? If you’re hoping that the reality you wrote out in your goal actually triggers some other, secondary reality, write that instead.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Validate:</strong> Now you can start showing your draft to others and asking for their opinion. You will know your circumstances best, but I’ve found it effective to frame it as an invitation: “Does this represent the work we do? What feels off?”</li> <li><strong>Finalize:</strong> Once you know your content is right, you can allow yourself a little space to refine the language – but only if you want. Once you have a goal and objective(s) that feel more right than wrong, put down the pen and start using it.</li> </ol> <p>I could spend a long time recommending frameworks that would make your draft goal better, punchier, easier to track, better aligned to your mission, but I wouldn’t recommend doing that for a rapid goal. If you can do goal-writing in a more intentional way, this style of rapid goal-writing no longer makes sense. Thankfully, there are a lot of resources out there for writing goals in an intentional way if that’s where you’re at – a subject for another post.</p> <h3 id="an-example">an example</h3> <p>Let’s run a rapid, intentionally imperfect example with the above steps.</p> <p>Let’s go back to the example we covered when talking about <a href="#on-ghost-goals">ghost goals</a>: Samantha’s team, who works at a nonprofit that offers coding classes to kids. If Samantha were to write a rapid goal with the above steps, it might look like:</p> <ol> <li><strong>Write what you’re tracking right now:</strong> Samantha could write something like: <ul> <li>Train 100 kids in coding.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Pull it up a level:</strong> Samantha could write a few things down, depending on what she believes the program is trying to do. For simplicity, let’s say Samantha writes: <ul> <li>Help kids build relevant skills for the workforce.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Refine:</strong> <ul> <li><strong>Specifics:</strong> <ul> <li>How do we define a “relevant skill” for the workforce? Is coding a relevant skill for all jobs in the workforce, or just some?</li> <li>Which kids do you want to participate in the program? Is this program for every kid who wants to join, or are you hoping certain kids participate?</li> <li>Who do we consider a “kid”?</li> <li>What would someone have to do to be considered “trained”? If a kid only participates in half of the training sessions, or leaves early every class, are they trained?</li> <li>Does the training prepare kids for any job, or is there a specific industry or type of job that the training prepares for?</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>Cause-and-Effect:</strong> <ul> <li>If participants do nothing but attend training – regardless of their experience with the training, if they liked it, if they can demonstrate certain skills – will they have relevant skills for the workforce? How would you know they’ve built the skills?</li> <li>Are there other things you’re doing to prepare them for the workforce? If so, those might be additional objectives.</li> </ul> </li> <li><strong>End State:</strong> <ul> <li>If your participants build the relevant skills, but not one of them gets a job, are you still satisfied with the work you’ve done? The answer absolutely could be yes – this is a sanity check, not a trick question!</li> </ul> </li> </ul> </li> </ol> <p>As you go through this exercise, you’ll likely feel the tension to press for a mission, to write out additional objectives, to make a perfect system. That energy is not your enemy, even as I encourage you to not act on it right now. If that’s how you feel when you write goals, that’s amazing – and maybe it’s time for a more intentional goal-writing process that starts with the mission and goals, not the metrics. If you’re truly in a place where you’re writing a rapid hypothesis for your 3-5 most used metrics, this is where I’d recommend you stop for now.</p> <p>Of course, the thesis of writing rapid goals is twofold: they’re better than no goals at all, and having imperfect goals will eventually create enough tension to instigate a more intentional goal-writing process. If you find yourself consistently stuck with rapid goals that never graduate to an intentional process, then it might be time to take a step back and interrogate why.</p> <h2 id="conclusion">conclusion</h2> <p>The curse of writing a blog post like this is that it has to be general and unspecific, in hopes that general and unspecific advice can be helpful to your situation. I hope I’ve given you enough reasoning why goals are important for your metrics, as well as a path to writing something more useful than not.</p> <p>I want to end where I started: this work is hard. It’s okay to start where you are, with what you have right now. I believe in iterative improvement, as long as the iteration continues. You might surprise yourself with where you land with steps that seem very small to start.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="goals"/><category term="metrics"/><category term="reporting"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[making the case that an imperfect goal that's used is better than none at all]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a long-form introduction</title><link href="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-longer-introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a long-form introduction"/><published>2024-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-03-24T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-longer-introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-longer-introduction/"><![CDATA[<figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bundokim_dogs.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> A corgi mix and poodle meet. Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@bundo?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Bundo Kim</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/brown-and-black-short-coated-small-dog-with-white-long-coat-small-dog-on-gray-concrete-NIKl5WwL-RE?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a> </div> <p>Because I’ve had a less-than-conventional path into data work, it feels appropriate to start this blog with a little more about me. How did I end up here (and why am I, as a former colleague once asked me, not a poet or a baker instead)? Where am I looking to grow (as all close to me know that I am fully, if sometimes overly, committed to growing towards <em>the next thing</em>)? And perhaps most importantly, how does all of this shape my approach to data work? I believe that the analysis can’t be divorced from the analyst, so consider this my longer-form introduction to me–and by extension, my approach to analytics and data work in general.</p> <h2 id="my-entrance-into-data">my entrance into data</h2> <p>I graduated college with minimal math exposure. No part of me identified as a “numbers person.” But the first full-time job I landed out of college–a Coordinator role for an evaluation team at a nonprofit–needed those “numbers” skills to answer the financial questions I was responsible for. So with nothing but a barely-supported edition of Oracle BI, an Excel license, and a grit I’ve come to love about myself, I set to figuring it out. I started with learning pivot tables in Excel. When I wanted the ability to see multiple tables in the same visualization, I graduated to data transformations and modeling in Power BI. When I learned about databases, I sought out SQL bootcamps and consulting projects for practice. And when I finally was starting to feel something close to analyst, I dove into learning pandas and matplotlib in Python. Over a few short years, I had completely pivoted my career towards data work.</p> <p>Learning data skills in a place like Oxfam also helped me become a generalist. I took a 3-month visual design course, learned feminist theory from the Gender Justice department, and used my Union professional development funds to start a project management (PMP) certification. My willingness to volunteer gave me facilitation and leadership experience as well: I revamped and co-led the Staff Development Committee for my Union, co-chaired the Young Women Professionals Employee Resource Group (ERG), participated in the Gender Resource Network, and led a community of practice for data practitioners called Data Pack. (More on that below.) Oxfam was full of opportunities to learn if you knew where to look, and I was on a very successful scavenger hunt.</p> <p>In 2019, I co-founded Data Pack, a staff-led community of practice dedicated to data, which catalyzed my learning in ways I couldn’t have imagined. We started with nine members and a $20 Udemy Power BI course I had paid for out-of-pocket. When I left Oxfam in 2022, we had grown to 40+ members, two learning groups, and a $3k or so annual budget. We had delivered a dozen or so Data Pack projects, which matched data work to Data Pack members who wanted to learn a new skill. We hosted social hours, problem-solving sessions, and feminist data ethics book clubs. Perhaps best of all, I had designed a ridiculous logo inspired by the Three Wolf Moon t-shirt. (If you look closely, there are numbers in the background of the Data Pack logo, which was real, copied-and-pasted Oxfam financial data. A long-running joke with myself that data without context is just background noise.)</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/datapack_logo.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250px" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/threewolfmoon_tee.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250px" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> The Data Pack logo, next to the <a href="https://www.bewild.com/products/three-wolf-moon-mens-big-face-t-shirt">style of 2000s t-shirts</a> that inspired it. </div> <p>Personally, I learned Power BI, SQL and (the start of) Python all through Data Pack funds and learning opportunities. Data Pack was transformational to my career, and whether or not it still exists at Oxfam today, it was really special. You can learn more about Data Pack in the Harvard Data Science Initiative talk I gave in 2021, available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4O_DIl0fJzU">Youtube</a> starting at 23:21.</p> <h2 id="taking-the-analyst-title">taking the (analyst) title</h2> <p>After almost six years at Oxfam, I had begun to question the role of international non-governmental organizations (INGOs)–or, at the very least, my role in them. I began looking for other opportunities. In May of 2022, I accepted full-time Analyst position at the City of Boston. I was placed on the Performance Management vertical, a team dedicated to telling the story of the City’s performance through data. (Not too far off from my old evaluation team at Oxfam.) The initial nervousness I felt about my experience level faded as I learned that Oxfam’s challenges were common across large organizations. The skills I had built in relationship and project management, in translating stakeholder needs into analytic products, in data visualization design, and in facilitation were all relevant. The only difference was that the City employs some 20,000 staff instead of a few hundred.</p> <p>That size and scale of the City’s workforce afforded a unique opportunity to test the staff-led model for data culture started by Data Pack. In November 2022, I led our first data culture pilot at the City: an 11-session learning cohort on JavaScript with 22 staff, using freeCodeCamp as our curriculum. It was a knockout success, earning a 4.7 satisfaction rating from participants, and producing many <em>bbgs</em> (baby bar graphs). Those familiar with d3.js will hopefully share our pride in getting bars-on-page, just a few months after starting to learn JavaScript from scratch:</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/bbgs.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> The JavaScript pilot's collection of baby bar graphs, which we built in d3. </div> <p>We delivered a total of four learning cohorts in 2023, including JavaScript. One was in Python fundamentals, and two more were dedicated to learning Power BI as part of the City’s transition to the tool. Overall, 55 unique staff across the City completed 50% or more of their cohort in 2023. Through all of this, I also earned a promotion to Performance Manager. This role, which I’m still in today, increased my responsibility in developing strategy for and formally leading Performance Management programs.</p> <h2 id="looking-ahead">looking ahead</h2> <p>So, what next? I don’t think it’s a terrible thing to be open to many paths. I know where my interests lie:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Expanding My Analytic Toolkit:</strong> I genuinely love building data tools, and there is no limit to learning something new in data. I’m interested in tinkering with Python packages I have yet to try out, refreshing my stats knowledge, keeping my SQL skills sharp, and allowing myself space to follow my fancies. This includes adding to my toolkit to better apply feminist approaches to data work!</li> <li><strong>Facilitating Great Data Conversations:</strong> I’m proud of the facilitation skills I’ve built over time, and I’d love to support more people to use data in their work through intentional convening. This can take many forms (and doesn’t necessarily require a professional setting!).</li> <li><strong>Building Additional Domain Expertise:</strong> The data world is large, and I’m eager to see how data is being used across a variety of socially-minded contexts, including in the private sector. What questions do other industries often ask of their data? What skill sets do they require?</li> <li><strong>Exploring Strategy:</strong> I’m learning how much I enjoy–and excel at–imagining what could be, and laying out the path to get there. Data Pack, and the City’s Data Culture Program, have all had some combination of strategic plans, performance measures, and theories of change. I’m looking for opportunities and projects than enable me to take on increased responsibility in developing and delivering on strategy. I’m particularly interested in applying this lens to organizational data culture work.</li> <li><strong>Learning Feminist Leadership:</strong> I’m continually obsessed with the building blocks required to be a fantastic feminist leader in the workplace. I’m interested in evaluating (and growing!) my leadership skills, as well as continuing to volunteer for non-hierarchical leadership opportunities.</li> </ul> <h2 id="ps-why-im-not-a-poet">(p.s. why I’m not a poet)</h2> <p>The truth is that I never dreamed of being a full-time poet. Most of the poets I idolized in high school (Billy Collins, Tony Hoagland, Li-Young Lee) were professors and published on the side, so that’s what I imagined for myself. I’d sit on desks and teach kids to see poetry as a window into the world, and into the worlds of others.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/tonyhoagland_narcissism.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250px" height="100px" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/li-younglee_rose.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250px" height="100px" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/billycollins_picnic.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="250px" height="100px" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Some of the poetry books on my high school bookshelf: "What Narcissism Means to Me" by Tony Hoagland, "Rose" by Li-Young Lee, "Picnic, Lightning" by Billy Collins </div> <p>So when I started my college career at the University of Vermont, English was an easy first choice for major. But as you might’ve guessed by now: I hate choosing just one thing. Since I had spent most of my life learning French and wanted fluency, I threw that in as a dual major. And because I was fascinated with the world, and how people made meaning within it, I minored in Religion for good measure.</p> <p>Had UVM been a better long-term home for me, I might’ve graduated with that dual degree. But when I arrived at Northeastern in the fall of 2012, I was informed that major was not offered. I had to choose one, or take a pre-set dual major path. Forever committed to <em>never</em> choosing just one, I decided to try out the French and International Affairs track, and that was first fork towards data work. In an introductory IAF course, I learned about Leymah Gbowee, a Liberian peace activist. There was no going back. Reflecting over a decade later, I don’t fully empathize with all the reasons my younger self wanted to go into social justice work–I wouldn’t have even used that term to describe what I was pursuing–but it boiled down to a core belief I still hold: if I could do something to make the world more worth living in, I should, and I would.</p> <p>Northeastern also afforded me the privilege of travel. I spent a year getting my heart broken in Dublin, Ireland and another six months attempting French fluency in Grenoble, France. The world was so much bigger than I had imagined. I saw that so much of my beliefs and preferences were learned, not inherent, and I learned to evaluate them through that lens.</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/grenoble.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Hiking in the French Alps while on study abroad in Grenoble, France. </div> <p>I graduated in 2016 hungry to work any job, anywhere with a soul. I had done a six-month internship at Oxfam America, and they were hiring a Receptionist. I knew folks in the organization, so when I applied, they offered me the temp position that would’ve otherwise been filled by an agency. And as is common, once I was inside the system, everything was easier. We can talk about the pipeline to full-time positions in organizations like Oxfam (flawed), but by February 2017, I had my first full-time, post-college role. I was the Coordinator for the evaluation and technology for development teams. I was responsible for managing projects, financial administration, and while I didn’t know it yet, analytics for both.</p> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/graduation.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> My grandmother, mother, and me at my graduation from Northeastern in May 2016. </div> <p>So why am I not a poet? The short answer is that I felt I could have more impact elsewhere–and that poetry would always be a home for me, regardless of where my paycheck came from. :heart:</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="about"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[reflecting on my path to data work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a future place for data thoughts?</title><link href="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-future-place/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a future place for data thoughts?"/><published>2024-01-20T12:03:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-20T12:03:00+00:00</updated><id>https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-future-place</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://amy-hood.github.io/blog/2024/a-future-place/"><![CDATA[<p>Well, it’s the new year! While I’m a firm believer that change does not come on a calendar’s schedule, I also love that this time of year is often accompanied by reflection and a deep (if not entirely warranted) optimism. In that spirit, I’m hoping that 2024 can be the year I return to writing, in both professional and poetic capacities. So consider this a very-visible placeholder in hopes that it will soon be replaced by some data thoughts - on visual design for data visualization, on feminist data ethics practices for analysts, on data culture work.</p> <p>I’m looking forward to it. :smile:</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="posts"/><category term="formatting"/><category term="links"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[setting some intentions for 2024]]></summary></entry></feed>